בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף Daf is צדי ב, Tzadi Beis,
92, and we pick up on the משנה. Mishnah. We're continuing to
discuss a worker's rights to
eat when he's doing the work and here we go.
אוכל פועל קישות אפילו בדינר. Ochel po'el kishut afilu b'dinar. So a
worker can eat like cucumbers even if, you know, even a דינר's
dinar worth. So meaning, and right, but the point being that, or
even if the one cucumber's worth a דינר, dinar, the way רש״י
Rashi says it. Anyway, the point being that even he can eat
even more than he is being paid for his work. כותבת ואפילו
בדינר, Koseves v'afilu b'dinar, or a כותבת, koseves, a dried date, right,
pressed date even also if it's worth
a
דינר. dinar. רבי אליעזר בן חסמא אומר, Rabbi Eliezer ben Chisma omer,
לא יאכל פועל יותר על שכרו. lo yochal po'el yoter al s'charo.
No, he can't eat more than his actual pay. וחכמים מתירים, Vachachamim
matirin, and the sages permit it, אבל מלמדין אדם, aval m'lamdin adam,
but here was added though is well technically you have that right,
you teach a person שלא יהא רעבתן, shelo yehei ra'avtan, do not
be overly gluttonous and, you know, stuff yourself. It is not wise
for
long-term. You might think right now you're, you know, getting everything you
can out of this
opportunity, וסותם את הפתח לפניו, v'isosem es hapesach lifanav, for the future
you're going to be slamming the door in your own face. Who's
going to want to hire you as a worker afterwards? So technically
you have the right, but it's not really in your best interest.
Okay.
Yes, it's a funny name. I don't know what חסמא Chisma is.
השם חסימה, Ha'shem Chasima, the whole in itself.
Oh, oh that's actually a fascinating point. You're right, I wasn't even
thinking about it. You're right, you're right, you're right. It's about חוסם
פי פרה, chosaim pi para, and here you have his name as
חסמא. Chisma.
Excellent point. Right. Excellent point. So now גמרא Gemara says, חכמים היינו
תנא קמא. Chachamim hainu Tanna Kama. The sages is the תנא קמא,
Tanna Kama, because both the תנא קמא, Tanna Kama, the anonymous voice
at the beginning, and the sages both say he's allowed to eat
more than his basic amount. So the גמרא Gemara says no, איכא
בינייהו אבל מלמדין. ika beineihu aval m'lamdin. No, the difference is that
the sages added this point about that you instruct him. תנא קמא
לית ליה מלמדין. Tanna Kama leis lei m'lamdin. The תנא קמא Tanna
Kama figures that's not our business to instruct him, let somebody, you
know, learn by their mistakes. ורבנן אית להו מלמדין, V'rabbanan is lehu
m'lamdin, and the rabbis say no, we try to instruct him. Right.
איבעית אימא, Iba'is eima, if you want I can say, איכא בינייהו
דרב אסי. ika beineihu d'Rav Assi. They're really debating רב אסי. Rav
Assi. Like this the גמרא Gemara always does if you have two
positions that sound like they're identical and wants to understand why they're
different and they might actually even be the same voice and just
repeating itself, but the גמרא Gemara uses it as an opportunity to
stick in and to identify other debates around this issue and say
maybe they're debating this other debate about this issue. So what's the
position of רב אסי? Rav Assi? דאמר רב אסי, D'amar Rav Assi,
אפילו לא שכרו אלא לבצור אשכול אחד, אוכלו. afilu lo secharo ela
livtzor eshkol echad, ochlo.
This is hilarious. I'm hiring you to harvest one cluster of grapes.
As you're picking that cluster of grapes, you're popping it into your
mouth. So you actually can eat not just more than your fee,
you can eat the entire produce that you were supposed to be
gathering. Okay, ואמר רב אסי, v'amar Rav Assi, now רב אסי Rav
Assi has another variation of this, אפילו לא בצר אלא אשכול אחד,
אוכלו. afilu lo batzar ela eshkol echad, ochlo. Let's say you're hired
to do the whole vineyard, okay, but right now you so far
all you've done for your job is you've just picked one. So
you might think like, you know, you're allowed to eat little by
little as you're going through your work, but to say oh, now
I picked one and now I'm going to stuff myself, you know,
before I even get onto the second one. So that second point
doesn't seem nearly as much of a חידוש chiddush as the first
point. And now the גמרא's Gemara going to tell us why you
needed to say both. Okay,
וצריכא, Utzrichi, you need to say both. דאי אשמעינן הך קמייתא, D'ee
ashmi'inan hach kamaisa, the first one, משום דלא איכא למיתב לכלי דבעל
הבית. mishum d'lo ika lemsav l'keilei d'ba'al habayis. There, there we could
actually say I understand why if it's only one cluster we let
you eat the whole thing. Why? Because there you have to choose.
Either I'm going to put it in the basket or I'm going
to eat it. So maybe you have a right to say I
don't want to give up my rights, you know, just for the
owner, for the owner. It's one or the other, so if I
have to choose between the owner and me, I'm going to choose
me. So that might have made sense because otherwise you're not going
to get to eat any grapes. Okay. So in that case, היכא
דלא איכא למיתב לכלי דבעל הבית, heicha d'lo ika lemsav l'keilei d'ba'al
habayis, that
you know because there's nothing else to put into the owner's basket,
meaning basically it's choosing between you and the owner, and maybe you
have a right to choose yourself. Okay. What other choice do you
have? אבל היכא דאיכא למיתב לכלי
דבעל הבית, Aval heicha d'ika lemsav l'keilei d'ba'al habayis, but when you
have actually you're going to actually be filling up the owner's basket.
So I might say in that case where you don't have to
really choose between you and the owner. It's really a question about
pacing yourself. So in that case, אימא ליתב ברישא והדר ליכול, eima
leisav b'reisha v'hadar leichal, I might say that in that case actually
first start putting it into the basket and then eat. Okay, and
don't go ahead and eat all you can, you know, before you've
gotten more done with your work. So if you have to choose,
choose for yourself. But if it's, but if you're going to basically
fill his, you know, his basket is going to get filled regardless,
maybe you're supposed to. So if you have to choose, choose for
yourself. But if you're going to basically fill his basket is going
to get filled regardless, maybe you're supposed to therefore pace yourself. Okay,
so that's one possibility. Protestant work ethic?
Right.
Oh, actually and I think I even I think I even misstated
the first the second position. The second position is I did state
it correctly that you are hired for the whole day but the
way רש"י Rashi at least says it is it doesn't mean after
you put the first cluster in you can then eat your fill.
רש"י Rashi says what it actually means is very this makes more
sense I'm re-reading רש"י Rashi now. It actually means similar to the
first point which is you can eat the very first cluster. Okay
so they're both the same point that you can eat that first
cluster that you pick. Okay the difference is in one case you
only hired for one cluster and in the other case you were
hired for the whole day. But either way רב אסי Rav Assi
is saying you can eat the very first cluster. So the גמרא's
Gemara saying had you just said the first case I would have
understood it. It's either you or the בעל הבית ba'al habayit so
let it be you. But in the second case where you're going
to get it anyway right the first cluster should not go to
you. The first cluster should go to the בעל הבית. ba'al habayit.
You should first start your work. Okay now the הוה אמינא hava
amina makes some more sense. Let's see that again. וצריכא: V'tzricha: דאי
אשמעינן הך קמייתא משום דלא איכא למיתב לכלבו של בעל הבית, d'ei
ashmeinan hach kamaita mishum d'lo ika l'meitiv l'chalvo shel ba'al habayit, there'll
be nothing left to go to the owner so therefore you're allowed
to choose yourself. אבל היכא דאיכא למיתב לכלבו של בעל הבית Aval
heicha d'ika l'meitiv l'chalvo shel ba'al habayit where you could give to
the owner and also give to yourself, אימא ליתיב ברישא והדר ליכול,
eima l'yeitiv b'reisha v'hadar leichol, first you should put it in the
owner's basket and then eat. You shouldn't take the first cluster for
yourself. Okay. ואי אשמעינן בהא, V'ei ashmeinan b'ha, and had you told
me the second case I would have understood why you're allowed to
do it. דאפשר לקיים לשניהם לבסוף, D'efshar l'kayem l'shneihem l'vasof, because even
though you're putting yourself first in the end you will fill up
the owner's basket. The owner will get something. That's obviously the case
that made more sense. אבל היכא דלא אפשר לקיים לשניהם לבסוף, Aval
heicha d'lo efshar l'kayem l'shneihem l'vasof, but if there's not going to
be any grapes to give the owner in the end, אימא לא,
eima lo, maybe wouldn't be allowed. צריכא, Tzricha, you need both. Okay
so anyway so רב אסי Rav Assi says though one way or
the other you're always allowed to take the first cluster for yourself.
So that's maybe what is being debated by the תנא קמא Tanna
Kamma and the חכמים. Chachamim. Okay now exactly who is saying what
it's hard to read into their words but anyway maybe that other
that point is what is being debated. אי בעית אימא, Ei bayit
eima, if you want you could say עיקולי דבי ניהי Ikulei d'bei
nayei what they're debating is רב, Rav, רב's Rav statement. אמר רב
מצאתי מגילת סתרים בי רב חייא. Amar Rav matzati megilat setarim bei
Rabbi Chiya. There's always interest. I found a hidden scroll in the
house of רבי חייא. Rabbi Chiya. So רש"י Rashi says the reason
it's hidden is because it has written in תורה שבעל פה Torah
she-be'al peh and you weren't supposed to write תורה שבעל פה. Torah
she-be'al peh. So if you were writing it you did not want
it I mean it wasn't like oh my god I'm viol- like
I smoke in the bathroom I don't want anybody you know whatever
like I don't want to get caught. Okay it wasn't that point
that you want you're hiding because you don't want to get caught
but you're hiding it because you don't want it to become public.
Because you don't want public published you know you don't want people
to take תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh and make it into
תורה שבכתב. Torah she-bichtav. I mean it's hard for us to relate
because we have all this written down. But if you actually think
about it meaning there's two good reasons why you would not want
to write down תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be'al peh. One of them
which we sort of have lost sight of well we actually have
lost sight of both of them. Okay but is that if it's
written down it becomes like hardened you know and and
and concretized and there's no it loses some of the ongoing fluidity
of what תורה שבעל פה Torah she-be'al peh is supposed to be.
The other part is is that when you write it down it
takes on the authority of תורה שבכתב Torah she-bichtav right. And the
written word like if it's the written word of God if the
only thing is תנ"ך Tanakh is the written word then it's giving
it a different level of authority. Okay so there are these types
of reasons you don't want to write it down. So if you
want to have your own little private notebook it's one thing right.
But it's not that that should then be the published תורה שבעל
פה Torah she-be'al peh so that's why you had to keep it
hidden. So meaning not to publicize it. מצאתי מגילת סתרים בי רב
חייא וכתוב בה, Matzati megilat setarim bei Rabbi Chiya v'katuv bah, it's
written in there now sometimes it's also interesting because the things that
are found in these מגילת סתרים megilat setarim are sometimes radical ideas.
Okay וכתוב בה איסי בן יהודה אומר, v'katuv bah Issi ben Yehuda
omer, איסי בן יהודה אומר כי תבא בכרם רעך בביאת כל אדם
הכתוב מדבר. Issi ben Yehuda omer ki tavo b'kerem re'echa b'vi'at kol
adam hakatuv medaber. Issi ben Yehuda says when you go into your
friend's
vineyard in the- we're not just talking about a worker. Anybody can
walk into your friend's vineyard and start eating the grapes. Okay now
you understand why you want to hide that. That's a little dangerous
information.
Just a straight interpretation of the פסוק. pasuk.
I know but yeah but parallel to the point about כי תבא
בכרם רעך ki tavo b'kerem re'echa maybe you're right.
Okay Bernie from Vermont there you go.
ואמר רב לא שבקי איסי חיי לכל בריה V'amar Rav lo shavki
Issi chayei l'chol birya and רב Rav says איסי Issi does not
allow anybody to live meaning imagine farmers everybody can just walk into
your field and start eating the grapes that's crazy. Okay now of
course it doesn't say that a farmer's not allowed to put or
vintner's not allowed to put a fence with you know with dogs
and you know around his his yard but nevertheless not everybody does
that it's not the way you grow wheat ever drive by you
know these things you have these big things of wheat like people
are not going to fence it in what are you talking about
so you you're not that's crazy that can't work at a societal
level.
אמר רב אשי אמריתה לשמעתא קמיה דרב כהנא, Amar Rav Ashi amrita
l'shma'ata kamei d'Rav Kahana, I said over this discussion to רב כהנא
Rav Kahana and how crazy this idea was. And רב כהנא Rav
Kahana had a way of explaining it. רב כהנא אמר דילמא בעושים
בסעודתם דעבדי ואכלי, Rav Kahana amar dilma b'osim b'seudatam d'avdi v'achli, רב
כהנא Rav Kahana said maybe איסי בן יהודה Issi ben Yehuda doesn't
mean that you can ממש mamash go סתם stam go into a
guy's yard and take his grapes I mean besides which like it's
trespassing. Maybe what he means is is that people are... Can self-appoint
themselves worker to the בעל הבית. balabos. So basically, you see this
guy's grapes that they need to be picked, and you go in
and you're allowed to pick them and put them in the basket
and do the job, and for the sake of this סעודתא, seudasa,
you'll be able to eat in the process. So meaning, that's a
middle midpoint. They're not explicitly hired by the בעל הבית, balabos, but
you have a right to help him out and do his work
for him if you're, you know, even without being hired, and just
to feed yourself in the process. That's how he would read the
פסוק. pasuk. והוא אמר לי, v'hu amar li, and he said back
to me, that doesn't solve the problem. אפילו הכי, afilu hachi, even
with that, ניחא ליה לאיניש לאוגורי אגורי ולכדפי לפרדיסיה, nicha leh l'inish
l'ogurei agurei u'lichdafei l'fardiseih, a person would much rather pay for a
worker to hire workers to pick his grapes or his garden, you
know, his whatever his what's it called when you have trees, not
a garden, what's it called, an orchard, to pick from his orchard,
ולא ליתו כולי עלמא ואכלי ליה, v'lo leisu kulei alma v'achlu leh,
rather than have a free-for-all and anybody can just come in and
put themselves to work and eat from it. I mean, you know,
total disaster. Okay, right. Okay, anyway. So anyway, maybe but okay, maybe
they're debating איסי בן יהודה Isi ben Yehuda or not. You know,
again, presumably the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma who doesn't have any who
doesn't express any reservation would assume to be taking the more liberal
approach here, you know, to allow it even if it to take
to take the first cluster and put it in your mouth, to
allow people even if they're not explicitly hired, whereas the חכמים Chachamim
who are hesitant, no no no, you try to teach a person
to do it the right way, presumably they're taking the more conservative
approach. So anyway, we have two other debates around this issue that
we want to read into the משנה. Mishnah. One minute, let's do
another one.
Okay, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, oh no actually that's the end of
that read of the משנה. Mishnah. Yes.
Yes. So the first version of איסי בן יהודה Isi ben Yehuda
is really way things are in the שמיטה Shmita year. Anybody can
come in, take the grapes. Right. So what would be the difference
between שמיטה Shmita year if the הלכה halacha really worked according to
איסי בן יהודה? Isi ben Yehuda?
What would be the difference?
Well, because you're allowed to you don't have to just eat it
at, you know, pop it in your mouth, you would be allowed
to gather totally. You know, in a שמיטה Shmita year you can
gather as much as you want. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this. Okay, איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, now they raised the question,
פועל משלו הוא אוכל או משל שמים הוא אוכל? po'el mishelo hu
ochel o mishel Shamayim hu ochel? This is a great question, and
this came up a little bit earlier by תוספות Tosafot by the
question about מעשר Ma'aser and קובע kovei'a and when is the moment
you take possession. When you are eating, is the תורה Torah basically
saying, you know, I mean, you could have phrased this maybe more
strictly, is the תורה Torah giving you the היתר hetter to eat
from the owner's grapes? Okay, that's like משל שמים, mishel Shamayim, so
it's also משל mishel the owner. Okay, but it's sort of like
if you could say maybe the owner doesn't own it either, but
you don't own it either, you know, you have just a היתר
hetter to eat these grapes while you're doing the work. This is
a gift that the תורה Torah gives you. Okay, or is it
משלו הוא אוכל? mishelo hu ochel? No, no, no. What the תורה
Torah is saying is that this is always considered to be part
of your payment, part of your fee. Okay, now, you know, so
it's a standard benefit that is but it's still coming from your
employer and but on the one hand, you know, and when you
take it, it's basically yours. You know, this grape is mine, it's
not just that I have a right to eat this grape, the
תורה Torah is giving me this right to eat this grape. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says למאי נפקא מינה, l'mai nafka mina, what
difference does it make? דאמר תנו לאשתי ובני, d'amar t'nu l'ishti u'vanai,
he says I don't want to eat it, I want it to
go to my wife or my son. Like, I don't know why
the גמרא Gemara doesn't give a classic נפקא מינה nafka mina which
is you turn around and you marry a woman with it, you
know, I mean, that's always the classic נפקא מינה nafka mina of
ownership. You know, הרי את מקודשת לי, harei at mekudeshet li, you
know, you're standing there next to Ruth in the field there and
whatever,
you pick the grape, והאשכול זה, v'ha'eshkol zeh, or something like this.
Anyway, but you know, but that raises an interesting question that at
like when because if it's yours, there's still the limit of אל
כליך לא תתן. el keilecha lo titein. Like, do not store it
up. So what constitutes, and that's an interesting question to be asking
throughout this, the transgression of אל כליך לא תתן? el keilecha lo
titein? If you have to eat it right there on the spot,
then it isn't really fully yours. Okay, are you allowed, so what
does that mean? It's yours but there are limits, there's it's yours
but you can't you can't take it home. So, okay, so maybe
so what what is my freedom to use it, whether I see
it as mine or whether I see it as not at, you
know, as just eating the owner's or a gift from or you
know, coming משמים? mi'Shamayim? So the גמרא Gemara says, let's wait a
minute, let's say it's going to be eaten, but not eaten by
you. Okay, you have your wife and your kids there and you
stipulate at the beginning with the owner and you say I'm going
to go through the field and I want my wife and kids
to be eating it, not me. Okay, now maybe you also stipulate
the maximum amount because that's two people eating, you're only one person,
maybe don't say my wife and my kid, maybe just say one
of them. Does that work or not? אי אמרת משלו הוא אוכל,
ei amart mishelo hu ochel, if it's basically part of your salary,
so יהבינן להו, yehavinan lehu, so then תוספות Tosafot sort of says
part of your salary means we view it as if it's always
sort of or implicitly like it's stipulated in every agreement. So if
that's true, you can like reassign
it. Okay, אבל אי אמרת משל שמים הוא אוכל, aval ei amart
mishel Shamayim hu ochel, but if it's
basically a... You the בעל הבית ba'al habayis
isn't giving you this at all. It's while you're working the תורה
Torah gives you this right. So who cares what you negotiate with
the בעל הבית, ba'al habayis, okay? You don't have a you have
that right and your kids do not have that right. So מאי
mai so what's the הלכה? halacha? תא שמע ta shema come and
hear.
אוכל פועל קישואין ואפילו בדינר. Ochel poel kishuyin v'afilu b'dinar. Okay. הכותבת
ואפילו בדינר. Hakoseves v'afilu b'dinar. You can eat the fruit even if
it's like a דינר'ס dinar's worth, even if it exceeds your fee,
your pay. אי אמרת משלו הוא אוכל, Ei amarta mishelo hu ochel,
if it is part of your salary, you know, if it becomes
yours and it's part of your salary. אוגר בדנקא אכיל בזוזא? Oger
b'danka achil b'zuza? Somebody would be hired for a sixth of a
דינר dinar and eat a דינר'ס dinar's worth? The benefits don't exceed
the salary. Okay. It would be impossible to imagine that you would
be given a benefit of your salary that would exceed the salary
if you see it as something that's essentially coming from the owner
to you and implicit in your salary and something you own. So
the גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי משל שמים הוא אוכל? Ella mai
mishul Shamayim hu ochel? So what do you want to say? You
want to say that it's a special right that the תורה Torah
gives him? So סוף סוף sof sof אוגר בדנקא אכיל בזוזא? oger
b'danka achil b'zuza? You still have the irony here, okay? This guy's
being paid only a dollar and he's eating ten dollars worth of
food. Now, but I do see you still sort of understand though
why the גמרא Gemara feels that that's not as problematic as the
first approach. The first approach, it's conceptualized as like a fringe benefit
of the salary, right? And therefore you assume that the benefits are
less than the salary itself. Whereas in the other, it's not part
of that negotiation of the owner and the worker, it's something the
תורה Torah gives you a right to do, you know? Anyway, the
גמרא Gemara says אלא מאי אית לך למימר רחמנא זכיי ליה. Ella
mai is lach l'meimar Rachmana zakkei lei. What would you say if
it's מן השמים? min haShamayim? Even if it exceeds the salary, the
תורה Torah gives you that right. הכא נמי רחמנא זכיי ליה, Hacha
nami Rachmana zakkei lei, so even if it's משלו הוא אוכל mishelo
hu ochel and it's seen as like part of the contract between
the owner and the employee, nevertheless the תורה Torah allows that to
be even exceeding the salary.
Okay, so we can't prove it from there. תא שמע, Ta shema,
come and hear. רבי אלעזר חסמא אומר Rabbi Elazar Chisma omer לא
יאכל פועל יותר על שכרו, lo yochal poel yoseir al secharo, that
you can't eat more. וחכמים מתירין, v'Chachamim matirin, and the Sages permit.
Now that's really the same debate. But מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי? mai
lav b'ha kamifligi? So we're going to try it again. Essentially, this
is what we just tried a minute ago, okay? דמר סבר משלו
הוא אוכל, d'mar savar mishelo hu ochel, that it's part of your
salary and therefore it cannot exceed the you know exceed the amount,
the base. ומר סבר משל שמים הוא אוכל, umar savar mishul Shamayim
hu ochel, no it's a right the תורה Torah gives you.
לא, Lo, what's different from
it's not, it's just the end of the משנה. Mishnah. לא דכולי
עלמא משלו הוא אוכל. Lo d'chulei alma mishelo hu ochel. But
it's different because here it's a מחלוקת. machlokes. And if it's a
מחלוקת, machlokes, there has to be something at the root of the
debate. So the גמרא Gemara says this is a reasonable thing to
think is at the root of the debate. Before we even had
it as a מחלוקת, machlokes, we just had it as a statement.
But now you have two opinions. So what's the debate about? So
presumably the easy thing to say is the debate is exactly about
this conceptual point, okay? So the גמרא Gemara says not necessarily. Maybe
the debate is about something else. והכא בכנפשך קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'chnafshecha kamifligi.
How do we the פסוק pasuk itself says the you know it
says what is it כי תבא בכרם רעך ואכלת ענבים כנפשך שבעך.
ki savo b'cherem re'echa v'achalta anavim k'nafshecha save'echa. As you know, to
fill your soul, as your desire. So what does that word as
your desire mean?
Okay. מר סבר כנפשך בדבר שמוסר נפשו עליו. Mar savar k'nafshecha badavar
shemoseir nafsho alav. That why does it say כנפשך? k'nafshecha? It's because
the תורה Torah is telling you מוסר. mussar. It doesn't just mean
the worker can eat his fill. The תורה Torah is telling you,
you know why the worker is allowed to eat the grapes? Because
workers risk their lives to make their salary, right? They climb up
trees, they know they work on big high-rise buildings, you know they
work in doing construction you know in the street and they get
run over. I mean people do, people have risky jobs, but that's
what they have to do in order to bring home you know
a salary. So given that workers risk their lives and their well-being,
this is a right you know this is a this is something
that is appropriate, you know this makes sense why the worker gets
it. Now if that's how you read it, that the תורה Torah
is underscoring why the worker deserves it, then the point could be
then it doesn't matter how much, you know even if it exceeds
the salary. The תורה Torah is sort of helping us you know
empathize with the worker and make us understand why he should get
this, so it understands it makes sense that you know it shouldn't
be a limit. He risks his life. בדבר שמוסר נפשו עליו. badavar
shemoseir nafsho alav. If he's risking his life, he should get it
even without a limit. ומר סבר umar savar no, כנפשך k'nafshecha is
telling you a totally different דרשה. derasha. מה נפשך אם חסמת פטור,
ma nafshecha im chasamta patur, the same way that if you muzzle
yourself you don't you're exempt, you don't get lashes, אף פועל אם
חסמתו פטור, af poel im chasamto patur, if you muzzle the worker
meaning you don't get lashes. You only get lashes for muzzling an
ox. You still have stolen from the worker, but you don't get
lashes. So it's a totally different דרשה. derasha. Okay, but it was
nice to imagine that when there's a מחלוקת machlokes it would have
been on this core question, this core conceptual question, but we say
maybe it's a more technical issue of how you read the word
כנפשך. k'nafshecha. תא שמע, Ta shema, let's try it again. This is
going to be a really good proof. נזיר שאמר תנו לאשתי ובני.
nazir she'amar tnu l'ishti u'vanai. A נזיר nazir who is working in
a vineyard and says, hey I can't eat it, I'd like my
wife to come with me and let her eat it, okay? אין
שומעין לו. ein shomin lo. You do not listen to him. Now,
if this was all part of a benefit between him and the
employer and the employer and the employee, why would you not be
allowed to stipulate that your wife can eat, right? And this actually
is exactly what we said the נפקא מינא nafka mina was, was
can I let my wife and kid eat? אי אמרת משלו הוא
אוכל, ei amarta mishelo hu ochel, and if it's really his own
that he's eating and it's part of his pay,
אמאי אין שומעין לו, amai ein shomin lo, why can't he stipulate
with the employer? So if it's מן השמים min hashamayim you understand.
The Torah didn't give him the right to eat something that would
have been a transgression, so he doesn't have the right. But if
it's between him and the employer, right, why can't he just stipulate
this? So the גמרא Gemara says no, התם משום לך לך
אמרין נזירה, סחור סחור לכרמא לא תקרב. hatam mishum lech lech amrin
nezira, schor schor l'charma lo tikrav. This is a famous line in
the גמרא Gemara which is used also by later פוסקים poskim to
say no, no, no, technically he actually could stipulate. It is משלו
mishelo and he could stipulate. But we're not happy with the fact
that a נזיר nazir is working in a vineyard. So in order
to fine a נזיר nazir that he's working in a vineyard, we
are going to say you are not going to use those grapes
even for your wife. Basically imagine that. You're working in a vineyard
and you're basically working and you're taking grapes and you have a
right to take the grapes but give it to your wife. We
are not happy with this whole situation, so we are going to
tell you you lose your right to the grapes in that situation.
So it's לך לך אמרין נזירה, lech lech amrin nezira, go go
we say to the נזיר, nazir, סחור סחור, schor schor, around around,
לכרמא לא תקרב, l'charma lo tikrav, don't even get next to the
vineyard. And here you're ממש mamesh hiring yourself to work in a
vineyard. So this is used by פוסקים poskim later to
explain why we will make גזירות gezeirot or safeguards, even if it's
not a technical גזירה, gezeira, meaning the Rabbis are all making גזירות
gezeirot and safeguards. But this is not a technical גזירה. gezeira. This
is more an attitude, why we could say even though technically something
is permissible, you should avoid it because you're getting too close to
dangerous territory. So it's not an actual, yes, but it's not an
actual גזירה, gezeira, it's just a general way of religious life is
to be safe. Yes, he's been waiting to ask on them.
Otherwise you'd if somebody owns a vineyard would be advertising for נזירים.
nezirim.
Exactly, exactly. Only נזירים nezirim need apply, because then you don't have
to give them any benefits. Right, it's like you're an employer and
you're saying you're only going to hire somebody who's already covered by
his or her spouse's health insurance. Right.
I'm going to add that to the שמועס. shmuze.
There you go. That's true, yeah. Exactly, exactly. Okay, so anyway the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, תא
שמע, Ta shma, come in here. So anyway that seemed to be
exactly our נפקא מינא, nafka mina, but we said no, no, no,
maybe that's a rabbinic safeguard. Listen now let's look at this one.
פועל, Poel, if it's not a נזיר, nazir, if it's a worker
שאמר תנו לאשתי ובני, she'amar tenu l'ishti u'vanai,
give to my wife and sons, אין שומעין לו, ein shomin lo,
you don't allow him, even a normal worker. So that seems to
be exactly our נפקא מינא nafka mina and it says explicitly that
it doesn't work, which seems to be מן השמים הוא אוכל. min
hashamayim hu ochel. אי אמרת משלו הוא אוכל, ei amarta mishelo hu
ochel, if he's eating his own and it's part of the stipulation,
אמאי אין שומעין לו, amai ein shomin lo, why not listen to
him? So he says no. מאי פועל נזיר, Mai poel nazir, what
does it mean a worker? נזיר. Nazir.
Which is crazy. Why would it if the point was about a
נזיר, nazir, why would it just say a worker? So the גמרא
Gemara says והתניא נזיר והתניא פועל, vehatanya nazir vehatanya poel, wait a
minute, one ברייתא braita speaks explicitly about a נזיר nazir and this
one speaks explicitly about a worker, so presumably we're not talking about
a נזיר. nazir. So it says no. מידי גבי הדדי תניין, Midi
gabei hadadi tanyan, who said that they were taught next to one
another? Maybe they're taught in different collections and they're not in conversation
with one another and the one that says פועל poel never heard
of the one that says נזיר, nazir, and it means a נזיר.
nazir. Of course why it would say פועל poel if it means
נזיר, nazir, as though the reason for the הלכה halacha is because
the guy is a נזיר, nazir, doesn't make any sense. Anyway תא
שמע, Ta shma, come again. מנא לן לפועל שאמר תנו לאשתי ובני
שאין שומעין לו, Mena lan l'poel she'amar tenu l'ishti u'vanai she'ein shomin
lo, how do you know you don't listen to one who says
let my wife and son eat? שנאמר ואל כליך לא תתן. Shene'emar
v'el kelyecha lo titein. Now that's very interesting, right? That seems to
be saying exactly that. You only have a right to eat it
yourself, you don't have any right to use it in any other
way. Okay, but it still seems to say to us that it's
only a right to eat and it is not something that basically
is yours. Okay, but anyway and once again we see that it
says any worker can't do it, so it seems clear מן השמים.
min hashamayim. So the גמרא Gemara says no. וכי תימא הכא נמי
נזיר, Vechi teima hacha nami nazir, we're talking about a נזיר. nazir.
אי הכי משום ואל כליך לא תתן, Ei hachi mishum v'el kelyecha
lo titein, you shouldn't say that the reason you can't do it
is because you're putting it into your vessel. You should really say
משום לך לך אמרין נזירה. mishum lech lech amrin nezira. You should
say it's because we want to keep the נזיר nazir away from
the vineyard because according to that basically it is permitted for a
normal worker, it's only forbidden for a נזיר. nazir. אמר אין הכי
נמי, Amar in hachi nami, you're right, it should have said that
the reason is stay away from the vineyard because you're a נזיר.
nazir. והאי דקתני לה בלשון פועל, Vehai d'katni lah b'lashon poel, but
since we decided for some bizarre reason to call a נזיר nazir
a פועל, poel, a worker, כדקרא דקרי ליה פועל, k'dikra d'kari leh
poel, we took a פסוק pasuk that's relevant to more general workers.
Which is of course
totally insane, right? Here the whole הלכה halacha you want to claim
the whole הלכה halacha is limited to a נזיר, nazir, it's about
a נזיר, nazir, but you decide to call a נזיר nazir a
worker which suggests it applies to everybody and use a פסוק pasuk
that would apply to. apply to everybody. But at the end of
the day, no no no, it’s only about a נזיר. nazir. Okay,
so obviously that’s a very weak answer. The simple sense of these
ברייתות braitas is clearly that it is not something that is yours
and that you can sort of renegotiate with the employer and give
it to your wife and kids, etc. It is something that is
only מן השמים הוא אוכל, min hashamayim hu ochel, and since it’s
only מן השמים הוא אוכל min hashamayim hu ochel you do not
have a position to renegotiate. Okay.
תא שמע, ta shma, come in here, but the גמרא gemara resists
that conclusion. השוכר את הפועל לקצץ בתאנים. hasocher et hapoel l'katzetz bite'enim.
Somebody hires a worker to go ahead and dry out figs. Now
actually this is interesting because רש"י Rashi points this out and תוספות
Tosafot struggles with this a little bit, but remember a worker is
only allowed to eat until when he’s dealing with the stuff that’s
already been harvested until the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha is until it
reaches גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. Now if you pick a date and
you want to eat it right away, it’s גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha,
okay, but because you are choosing to dry them out, okay, and
to you know and to make them whatever dried dates, you have
pushed off the end of the גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, which means
that the own that the worker is now still entitled to eat
if he’s working it and it also means that he’s exempt from
מעשר maaser because you have now you just decided what you’re going
to do with these grapes, right? So that’s very important, right? It’s
not like there’s this objective reality, it’s גמר מלאכה gmar melacha now.
In some certain things it depends what your intention is. תוספות Tosafot
wonders whether it might depend less on your intention and more on
the standard practice of the place. If the standard practice of the
place is to dry them out, it’s not גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha,
if the standard practice is
is to eat it right away, it is גמר מלאכה gmar melacha
even if you’re choosing to dry it out. Okay, so there’s an
interesting question which would determine like your intention or the practice of
the place. But anyway, in this case the גמר מלאכה gmar melacha
is not till it's dried, and you've been hired for that. So
הרי זה אוכל ופטור מן המעשר, harei zeh ochel u'patur min hamaaser,
you can eat because it’s not גמר מלאכה gmar melacha and you’re
exempt from מעשר. maaser. על מנת שיאכל אני ובני או שיאכל בני
בשכרי, al m'nat she'yochal ani u'vni o she'yochal bni bis'chari,
now let’s say you say on the condition that I and my
son will eat, or that my son will eat for my fee.
Okay, now what does it mean that he will eat for my
fee? בשכרי. bis'chari. So רש"י Rashi says it means that instead of
you owe me ten dollars for the per hour, we’ll be very
generous, ten dollars per hour, you know and for those days I’m
sure, ten dollars per hour plus I get to eat the you
know I get to eat these dates, okay, I want I want
you to deduct from my ten dollars an hour anything my son
is going to eat. My son will eat as I’m working and
you’ll deduct that from my ten dollars an hour. That’s the way
רש"י Rashi explains it. תוספות Tosafot says no no no, what it
means בני בשכרי bni bis'chari means my son in my stead. You're
still going to give me my ten dollars an hour, but instead
of me eating my son is going to eat. Okay, so anyway
one way or another the son is also eating here, okay. So
הוא אוכל ופטור, hu ochel u'patur, he eats and he’s exempt from
מעשר maaser because he’s eating because the תורה Torah gave it to
him.
ובנו אוכל וחייב, u'vno ochel v'chayav, and his son eats and the
son has to take מעשר maaser because his son eats because that
was the stipulation with the owner, but he has to take מעשר
maaser because for the son it’s more like a purchase, right? And
remember when there’s a sale, right, that’s קובע koveia and that obligates
it in מעשר. maaser. So the גמרא gemara says one minute, ואי
אמרת משלו הוא אוכל, v'i amrat mishelo hu ochel, now if you
say that he’s eating his own stuff,
it’s part of what was negotiated with the בעל הבית, baal habayit,
okay,
בנו אמאי חייב, bno amai chayav, why is the son חייב chayav
in מעשר, maaser, which means what? So רש"י Rashi says hold on
let me just read רש"י Rashi again.
Oh right, so this is the way רש"י Rashi reads it very
very ingenious. רש"י Rashi says look, if in general when we say
a פועל poel eats, it’s because that is seen as a type
of a benefit and a type of his fee from the from
the you know and his pay from the owner, that means that
even though it is your pay you’re פטור patur from מעשר, maaser,
right, that’s part of the חידוש, chiddush, okay. Yes, yes, this is
your pay and you’re פטור patur from מעשר. maaser. So we don’t
see the fact that it’s his pay as a type of a
מכר mecher or sale to obligate it in מעשר. maaser. So if
that’s true in general, you say a worker can eat without taking
מעשר maaser even if we see it as type of his pay
משלו, mishelo, so then and we don’t see it as a מכר,
mecher, so then why when he allows his son to eat by
virtue of his pay does the son have to take מעשר? maaser?
That’s no different than him, it’s all stuff he’s getting in his
pay and you’re telling me he doesn’t have to take מעשר. maaser.
Okay, so let’s read that again. ואי אמרת משלו הוא אוכל, v'i
amrat mishelo hu ochel, if you say that in general a worker
is eating as part of his salary essentially and nevertheless he’s exempt
from מעשר, maaser, so בנו אמאי חייב, bno amai chayav, so why
when his son is eating as part of the salary is the
son חייב? chayav? אמר רב פפא משום דמיחזי כמקח. Amar Rav Pappa
mishum d'mechzi k'mekach.
Technically you’re right, but it looks like a sale when you’re chomping
as you’re eating, however we conceptualize it, it’s no in both cases
it’s not technically a sale, in both cases it’s a salary, okay,
but in but when you’re chomping and eating, you know it... Doesn't
look like a sale, you're the worker, you're just nibbling, etc. Okay?
It doesn't, whereas if you give it to someone other than yourself,
right, then that looks like, however the arrangement was behind the scenes,
it looks like there was a transfer of ownership and it looks
like a sale, right, and therefore, you know, that's something that at
least rabbinically you're חייב chayav in מעשר. maaser. Yes, Charlie.
The biblical obligation of tithing is grain, wine, and oil.
Yeah, this is all rabbinic.
This is all rabbinic.
True. Okay, now, תא שמע, Tashma, come and hear. השוכר את הפועל.
Hasocher et hapoel. Okay, now here's a nice case. You hire a
worker לעשות בנטע רבעי laasot beneta revai and all of your trees
here, it's their fourth year, okay, which means, and it's outside of
ירושלים, Yerushalayim, which means that the worker will not be able to
eat the fruit. Okay,
so
בנטע רבעי שלו הרי אלו לא יאכלו. beneta revai shelo harei elu
lo yochalu. Obviously they can't eat and they can't take it home
and be פודה podeh or whatever, because you know the whole permission
is to eat right away. Okay, ואם לא הודיעם. Veim lo hodiam.
Now let's say you forgot to mention it to them, right? So
that's a little bit unfair. They were coming and they were assuming
they were going to get to eat from the tree as they
worked and you forgot to mention to them, forgot, that it was
נטע רבעי. neta revai. So what do you have to do is
the following: פודה ומאכילן. Podeh umachilan. You have to redeem the fruit,
okay, and then feed it to them because basically it's like, hey,
you know, they were assuming to get ten dollars worth of eating
out of it, they didn't, you have to make it up to
them. How do you make it up to them? You redeem ten
dollars worth of the fruit and you give it to them, okay?
Because you're allowed to obviously redeem נטע רבעי neta revai outside of
ירושלים. Yerushalayim. It works like מעשר שני. maaser sheni. Okay, so now
let's understand why you still have this legal obligation to them. אי
אמרת משל שמים הוא אוכל למאי פודה ומאכילן? Ei amart mishel shamayim
hu ochel lemai podeh umachilan? If it is just something that's not
part of your salary commitment to the worker, this is just some
right that the תורה Torah gives them, okay, so why do you
have to then make it up for them if they didn't have
it? איסורא לא זכה ליה רחמנא. Issura lo zachar leh rachmana. The
תורה Torah never gave them a right with נטע רבעי. neta revai.
So it's not like I- you were expecting more benefits and you
tricked me and I wasn't getting the benefit I was expecting. You
weren't getting those benefits from me, right? You were getting them from
God. That was not part of our negotiation, right? If it's seen
as a benefit that comes along with it that you are getting
from your employer, then you could say, you know, this, you cheated
me, this was an implicit benefit which you're not giving me. But
here it's just, no, you know, if you want to eat from
the grapes, great, that's not a טענה taana you have about me,
that's your מצוה, mitzvah, that's your right מן התורה, min hatorah, and
you figure out whether you have that right or not. Okay? So
the גמרא Gemara says
no, התם משום דמיחזי כמקח טעות. Hatam mishum demichzei kemekach taus. No,
no, no, it doesn't matter if technically speaking, you know, that wasn't
something you were giving them and it was something God was giving
them. Nevertheless, they feel deceived. Okay? They believed that they were going
to have a right, fine, not from you, they believed that they
were going to have a right מן התורה, min hatorah, but they
were reasonably expecting to be able to have some benefits, okay? So
even if you didn't cheat them because it wasn't directly part of
your negotiation with them, right, it wasn't part of your relationship with
them directly, nevertheless, it looks very unfair and you want to address
that situation. All right, so אימא סיפא, eima seifa, now let's look
at the end of this. נתפרצו עיגוליו. Nitparzu igulav. Let's say you
have these rounds of pressed figs. I keep on forgetting which is
the figs and which is the dates, actually this might be pressed
dates. דבילה, Dveila, I think they said.
Yeah, before we were talking about figs, I might have said dates
before, I always get confused. So many things. I know. Anyway, before
we were talking about figs, now I think we're talking about dates.
I don't believe it's figs.
They say figs? All right, I don't know what I'm talking about.
Okay, fine, moving on, I don't
care. Anyway, okay, you have these- you have these pressed rounds of
figs. Anyway, I relate to pressed figs more because that's what I
buy in the supermarket, I don't buy pressed rounds of dates but
I buy these pressed rounds of figs. Anyway, so you have, now
they are גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, okay? המלאכה Hamellacha is done, so
after this point, the worker doesn't have any right to eat. What
happens though is that the whole thing, I had all these big
pressed rounds of figs and something happened and they all collapsed and
they all scattered. And now I got to hire a worker to
regather them and repress them. Here's the only thing, the worker doesn't
realize it was גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. But the worker thinks that
these were never pressed. He thinks it wasn't גמר מלאכה gmar melacha
and he's going to have a right to eat from them, okay?
נתפרצו עיגוליו, Nitparzu igulav,
נתפתחו חביותיו, nitpatechu chaviyotav, or the barrels of wine opened up, we're
going to have to see how barrels of wine fit into this,
let's bracket that for a moment, הרי אלו לא יאכלו. harei elu
lo yochalu. They don't have a right to eat because it's גמר
מלאכה. gmar melacha. ואם לא הודיעם, Veim lo hodiam, but if you
didn't inform them that it was גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha,
מעשר, maaser, you have to take מעשר maaser from it because right
now it's גמר מלאכה, gmar melacha, you have to take מעשר, maaser,
and a worker's right to eat is after מעשר, maaser, is without
מעשר, maaser, so you take מעשר maaser and then you give them
from it to eat. Okay, so once again, they were expecting they
would have the right and they didn't, you have to make it
up to them. That makes sense if it's משלו, mishelo, it's seen
as part of your contract with them. But ואמרת משל שמים אוכלו,
ve'amarta mishel shamayim ochlo, but if it's not part of your contract,
if it's some right they have from heaven, so הוא אוכל, hu
ochel, אמאי מעשר ומאכילן, amai ma'aser umachilan, why is that your responsibility
to feed them? איסורא לא זכי לה רחמנא, issura lo zachih lah
rachmana, the Torah didn't give them something that was אסור, asur, meaning,
here it's funny to use the word אסור, asur, you could just
say they don't have a right because it's גמר מלאכה, g'mar melachah,
but part of the גמר מלאכה g'mar melachah is that it's חייב
chayav in תרומות ומעשרות. trumos u'ma'asros. So once it's טבל tevel they
don't have a right. Okay, but anyway, this is just not a
right they have from the Torah, let them go complain to God
or whatever. This wasn't part of your negotiation. Okay. So the Gemara
says, no, וכי תימא הכא נמי משום מחזי כמקח טעות, vechi teima
hacha nami mishum machzei kemekach taut, let's say it's the same reason.
You're right, technically speaking, they have no טענה taina against you, it
wasn't part of your negotiation. Okay, but it still looks like a
מקח טעות mekach taut because, you know, they were still reasonably expecting
it and they're not going to get it. So they still, you
know, it still looks like you tricked them, even if technically speaking
it wasn't your deal with them. Okay, so say that's the reason
here too. All right, let's just figure out how that makes sense.
בשלמא נתפרצו עיגוליו, bishlama nitpartzu igulav, I get the idea when your
figs' sort of rounds break up, מחזי כמקח טעות, machzei kemekach taut,
they look at it and they see that it looks like it's
not גמר מלאכה g'mar melachah and therefore they think they're entitled to
it,
and it looks like they were cheated. אלא אי נתפתחו חביותיו, ela
i nitpatchu chavyotav, מאי מקח טעות איכא? mai mekach taut ika? But
what type of mistake can they have when the barrels of wine
open? Right, the wine is obligated in תרומות ומעשרות trumos u'ma'asros when
it becomes wine, when it goes into the wine vat, when it's
being pressed. So even if they see a barrel that basically has
a hole in it and the wine is spurting out and they
have to now, you know, plaster over the barrel, they obviously know
it's גמר מלאכה, g'mar melachah, so what type of מקח טעות mekach
taut is there? Of course, that question has nothing to do with
this issue of משל שמים mishel shamayim or משלו. mishelo. It's just
explaining the ברייתא. braita. Why does the ברייתא braita say that if
you didn't tell them, you have to make it up to them?
What were they misunderstanding about the wine case? The wine case obviously
was גמר מלאכה. g'mar melachah. What was it you were supposed to
tell them? How in any way were they uninformed? So that's just
a question.
The wine spilling all over the place.
Yeah. As I... right, it's also a question about the urgency of
it, like how do you have time to negotiate? But I don't
get that exactly either. But anyway, but the Gemara is saying, where
is there any lack of informing them? It's clearly גמר מלאכה. g'mar
melachah. The Gemara says, והתניא, vehatanya, I'm sorry, so, one minute, מאי
מקח טעות איכא, mai mekach taut ika, so מידע
ידע דאית להו למעשר. meida yada de'it lehu lema'aser.
It's obvious that it's obligated in מעשר ma'aser and they're not entitled
to, which is just a question on the ברייתא. braita. So אמר
רב ששת, amar Rav Sheshet, שנתפתחו חביותיו לבור. shenitpatchu chavyotav labor. Ah,
what happened was, was your barrels, you know, you were, I
don't know, somehow you were barrelling them right in the, I don't
know where you barrel the wine, I don't know if that's the
right verb.
Anyway, but wine cellar.
That's where you bring the barrels, but anyway, but you have them
all, the wine collects in a wine, in a wine vat, a,
you know, a pit where it's sort of being pressed and it
goes into. And then from there, you put them into the barrels.
So apparently, assuming that you put them into the barrels right at
the edge of the pit. So there you are, you're putting them
into the barrels and then the, you know, the wine vat was
completely emptied from all the wine. And then something happened and I
don't know, a hurricane or whatever, some kid on a bike or
whatever happened, and all the barrels broke and all the wine spilled
back into the בור. bor. Okay, and now you hire somebody to
barrel the wine. So in that case, the person thinks that maybe
it never was גמר מלאכה. g'mar melachah. It never got out of
the בור. bor. They think that this is the wine that originally
fell into the בור. bor. Okay. I don't know why they don't
see broken barrels all over the place, but okay, you clean that
up. Okay, so the Gemara says, but it doesn't matter, even if
they think the wine never came out of the בור, bor, it
still should be גמר מלאכה. g'mar melachah. והתניא, vehatanya, we taught in
the ברייתא, braita, יין משיריד לבור, yayin misheyerid labor, that as soon
as the wine goes into the vat, that's when it's גמר מלאכה.
g'mar melachah. So what reasonable mistake, what mistake are they making? So
the Gemara says, no, רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, maybe we're going like
רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. דאמר רבי עקיבא, de'amar Rabbi Akiva, משיקפה, misheyikpeh,
that the wine, it's not enough that it goes into the pit,
basically what you have to do is that the, the, the, the
lees, you know, like the skin and the pits or whatever, they
have to like float to the top and you have to remove
that stuff that has floated to the top, and only then is
it גמר מלאכה. g'mar melachah. It's not enough that the juice is
in the pit. Okay, and therefore somebody sees it and thinks that
it's not גמר מלאכה. g'mar melachah. He thinks that process hasn't been
done yet, and therefore he thinks he's going to have a right
to eat, and he doesn't, and it looks like מקח טעות, mekach
taut, and you have to make it up to him. Okay, so
the Gemara says,
דאמרי ליה, de'amri leh, because they can say to him, לאו ידענא,
lav yadeana, we did not know that it was not,
that the, the, the lees have already been removed. So the Gemara
says, ולימא להו, velima lehu, so still, why is it a legitimate
מקח טעות mekach taut type of a claim? He could say back
to them, איבעי לכו לאסוקי אדעתייכו, ibei lachon le'asukei adatayichu, because he
says, listen, you maybe didn't have to think about the fact that
maybe barrels broke and the wine spilled back in, but I hire
you to come put the wine from the vat into the barrels,
and you know that גמר מלאכה g'mar melachah is when the, the
lees. removed, you should have realized that it's reasonably possible that the
גמר מלאכה gmar melacha already occurred, right? Maybe the lees have already
been removed, right? So, forget the issue of the barrels. Why do
you have a complaint to me that, oh, I thought I was
still going to have a chance to do it? If
all you knew was that it was in the pit, but maybe
the lees were already removed and maybe it was already גמר מלאכה,
gmar melacha, that was your responsibility to figure that out. So the
גמרא Gemara says no, באתרא דהוא גברא דנגיד איהו מקפי. ba'asra dehu
gavra denagit ihu makpe. It's a type of a place where it's
understood that the jobs go together. The guy you hire to do
the barrelling is the guy you hire to remove the lees of
the wine. And since that's the normal way the job is packaged,
they see wine in a pit, they don't realize the barrels have
broken, they don't realize that the lees are not there, they're being
hired to barrel it. Normal people who are being hired to barrel
are the ones that are removing the lees and therefore the ones
that are entitled to the wine, and therefore since that isn't the
case you have to make it up to them. If it's משלו
mishlo then it's a real sense of מקח טעות mekach taut because
that really was implicitly part of your negotiation, and even if it's
משמים mishamayim it still מחזי כמקח טעות. mechzi kemekach taut. Yes, Rabbi
Dove.
Are we sure that the barrels have broken?
In רש"י Rashi meaning where he says
נתפתחו חביותיה שניתקו מגופיהן ונחלו לתוך גומן. nitpatchu chavioteiha shenitku migufeihen venichalu
letoch guman.
Yeah, you're right. רש"י Rashi says, I'm sorry, you're right. I've been
saying broken because I was trying to figure out a case.
I just want to see a realistic case.
Yeah, yeah, yeah, you're right. I'm sorry, you're right. So I was
sort of, maybe I was saying it because they were all spilled
back into the בור bor and I was trying to imagine a
case... cistern. Thank you. Trying to imagine a case like that. But
רש"י Rashi says that it basically just means that like the seal
has been removed and you're hiring them to put the seal back
on.
They're standing there open.
Yeah, but if,
but again, but like that's, but once the גמרא Gemara then turns
it, you're right, the simple נתפתחו nitpatchu just means the, like you
would have a wax seal or some type of a tar seal
and it had been removed and now you have to put it
back. That's just an error of judgment. Well, no, because now the
גמרא Gemara is saying the only way you can make a mistake
and think you'd be entitled is if it all fell back into
the cistern. So that I can't understand how it happens just by
an opening. I imagine that the wine is spilling out out of
control. Alright, so the גמרא Gemara says, but you're right, נתפתחו nitpatchu
just means it was opened. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like
this: והשתא דתני, vehashta detanya, now that we've taught, רב זביד בדבי
רבי אושעיא, Rav Zvid bidei d'Rabbi Oshaya, רב זביד בדבי רבי אושעיא
Rav Zvid bidei d'Rabbi Oshaya teaches that there's a different, that the
debate is different than we thought in terms of when the wine
is גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. יין משיורד לבור ויקפה, Yayin misheyered labor
veyekpeh, the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma says already one step further, that
it has to go into the cistern and have the stuff removed.
רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, and רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva goes
even a later
position, משישלה בחביות. misheyishleh bechaviyot. Now ישלה בחביות yishleh bechaviyot רש"י Rashi
says is once you pour it into the barrels apparently it like
bubbles up and there's also some froth on the top and you
have to like remove some of that froth on the top. It's
another sense of removing something, okay, once it's already in the barrels.
So once that's true, אפילו תימא שלא נתפתחו חביות אף לבור, afilu
tema shelo nitpatchu chaviyot af labor, we don't have to have the
case that the barrels spilled into the cistern. That you just have
an open barrel and you're hiring them to put the top back
on the barrel and to reseal the barrel. And all you have
is an open barrel, okay, and but nevertheless they think it's not
גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. Why? Because they think this froth hasn't been
removed, according to רבי עקיבא. Rabbi Akiva. לבור
דאמרי ליה, labor de'amrei lei, they say to him, לאו ידינא דמשלי,
lav yedina demishleh, we didn't know that this froth was removed yet.
You were hiring us to cover and seal the barrels, so we
thought we were going to be entitled to drink from the wine.
So ונימא להו, venimra lahu, let him say back to them, איבעי
לכו לאסוקי אדעתייכו דילמא משלי. ibaye l'chu l'asukei ada'ateichu dilma mashli. Why
did you have a right to assume that it wasn't גמר מלאכה?
gmar melacha? You know, maybe the froth had been removed and therefore
it was גמר מלאכה. gmar melacha. So no, באתרא דהוא דשריק איהו
משלי. ba'asra dehu desharik ihu mashli. No, the guy, the place where
the guy who sort of, you know, puts the seal on the
barrel is the one whose job it is to remove the froth.
So I'm hiring you to put the seal on the barrel, normally
that's packaged together with removing the froth. You have a reasonable expectation
that you're going to eat, but as it happens to happen, this
actually had already been done, the froth was removed, it had already
been sealed, it just became unsealed, and therefore you don't have it.
Okay, so if it's משלו mishlo I really cheated you and therefore
I have to give, you know, pay you, give you that amount,
take מעשר ma'aser and give you that amount. And if it's משמים
mishamayim it looks like I cheated you. Okay, even though it wasn't
directly part of our negotiation, it still looks like a מקח טעות.
mekach taut. Okay, so תא שמע, ta shema, let's try again. קוצץ
אדם על ידי עצמו על ידי בנו ובתו הגדולים על ידי עבדו
ושפחתו הגדולים. Koteitz adam al yedei atzmo al yedei bno ubito hagedolim
al yedei avdo veshifchato hagedolim. I can go to the בעל הבית
ba'al habayit and I have my whole family, this happens, like migrant
families that are hired to harvest. And I go and I represent
my family to the בעל הבית ba'al habayit and I say here's
the deal, okay, we are going to forgo our right to eat
the grapes, okay, and you are going to pay us an extra
two dollars an hour. Okay, and we work out that deal. I
can do that representing myself, or representing my adult children, my wife,
my adult slaves, I can do that. Okay,
קוצץ אדם koteitz adam ועל האשה מפני שיש בהן דעת, ve'al ha'isha
mipnei sheyesh ba'an da'at, because they have דעת da'at and therefore they...
can be מוחל, Mochel, forgo their rights in exchange for higher pay,
there you know I can and I can represent them in that
process. אבל אינו קוצץ על ידי בנו ובתו הקטנים Aval Eino Kotzetz
Al Yadei Beno U'Vito HaKetanim ולא על ידי עבדו ושפחתו הקטנים Velo
Al Yadei Avdo VeShifchato HaKetanim ולא על ידי בהמתו. Velo Al Yadei
Behemto. I cannot represent my minor children or my minor slaves. Why?
Because they are not in a position to give up their right.
They can't give up their right to eat the grapes. They can't
be מוחל. Mochel. So I can't trade their right to eat the
grapes for a higher price because they can't give it up. Okay,
that's why I can't represent my minor children or my minor slaves.
Why can I not represent my בהמה, Behemah, my animal? Because as
רש״י Rashi points out, the animal doesn't have דעת, Da'at, but besides
which the animal issue is that I'm not allowed to muzzle even
my own animal. So by the animal case, right, it doesn't matter
whether whether you know somebody has an obligation to feed my animal
or not. The prohibition to muzzle is irrespective of the financial arrangement.
So whatever financial arrangement I make to tell you, whatever financial arrangement
you make, I can say to you, Dov, you give me more
money, I'll give you a right to muzzle my ox. You can't
say that because you never have a right to muzzle. You can't
even muzzle your own ox.
So why is it in the list?
Because it's another case where you don't have a right to make
a financial arrangement.
No, I get it, but...
Okay, it is different.
It is for different... גדר? Geder?
Yes, that's true. I know, I know. But רש״י Rashi does point
that out. Okay, anyway,
okay, now, now how is this relevant? Let's take a look.
I don't understand something. Yes. You say the minor son, right? Yeah.
What's the initial understanding? Say he brings his minor son. Is it
that he doesn't have to say I'm giving this up for my
if I want if he wants his son to eat, he can
have he and his son eat, right?
Okay,
he can say I'm giving up my right to eat if you
increase my pay, but he can't say my son is giving up
his right to eat if you increase his pay.
But the point I'm making is what is the minor son's right
actually?
He's a worker. There's no laws against against like you know that
you can't hire minors. He's a worker. He's all these people are
workers.
He's his own right, too?
Yeah. He has his own right. He's not through his father. They're
all working. The father's just representing them in negotiating with the בעל
הבית. Ba'al HaBayit. Okay. So קסלקא דעתך, Kasalka Deitach, now we're assuming
ומעלה להן מזונות, U'Ma'aleh Lahen Mezonot, that the father is feeding his
kids and his slaves, his minor slaves. Okay, now, when a father
feeds his kids and his minor slaves, he's entitled to their labor.
Okay, so here's the question. Here's a very nice נפקא מינה. Nafka
Mina. If it's משמי שמיא הוא זכי, Mishamei Shamaya Hu Zachai, then
this is not some salary they get that then gets transferred to
the father. This is just a right they have to eat. Okay,
so it's not a monetary issue that now the father now owns
this. Okay, but if it's משלו הוא אוכל, Mishelo Hu Ochel, if
it's seen as implicitly part of that financial arrangement, okay, then the
same way he's entitled to any salary that they earn, he's entitled
to any grapes, any benefits that are part of that salary. So
why can't he negotiate it away? It essentially it's his money. Okay.
So, okay, now קסלקא דעתך Kasalka Deitach we're assuming ומעלה להן מזונות
U'Ma'aleh Lahen Mezonot that he is feeding them and therefore entitled to
their salary. אי אמרת בשלמא משמי שמיא הוא אוכל, Ei Amart Bishlama
Mishamei Shamaya Hu Ochel,
if you say that it is just a right they have from
heaven, משום הכי אינו קוצץ, Mishum Hachi Eino Kotzetz, he can't negotiate
their right from heaven. אלא אי אמרת משלו הוא אוכל, Ela Ei
Amart Mishelo Hu Ochel, if a worker eats as part of his
salary, קטנים נמי נקוצצו, Ketanim Nami Nikotzetzu, let him negotiate the minor's
salary because the minor's salary is his. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, הכא במאי עסקינן כשאין מעלה להן מזונות. Hacha Bemai Iskinan Keshein
Ma'aleh Lahen Mezonot. We're talking that he's not feeding them. And since
he's not feeding his minor kids, he doesn't have a right to
their salary, and that's why even if it is seen as part
of their salary, he's not in a position to negotiate it. אי
הכי, Ei Hachi, if that's true, גדולים נמי, Gedolim Nami, so how
about adults? Why can he negotiate his you know wife's salary away
and why can he negotiate his adult slaves? So the גמרא Gemara
says no, גדולים ידעי וקמחli. Gedolim Yad'ei VeKamachli.
Why? They're adults, they're בני דעת, Bnei Da'at,
they can basically give him that right. They can say you know
we allow you to go ahead and negotiate for us and we'll
be מוחל Mochel on it, and you know and we'll get a
greater pay or whatever the case might be. Okay, so nobody's being
fed. He doesn't have rights to anybody's salaries. Nobody is necessarily like
that this is you know
indebted to him or grateful to him because he's not feeding them.
But nevertheless, even though the adults are not grateful, which might have
been a reason for them to agree, they still can agree to
have him negotiate for them. But the minors cannot, and therefore it
does not work. So that's explanation number one. It could be that
it would be salary, but he's not entitled to it because he's
not feeding them. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara goes on. והתני
רב אושעיא, Veha Tani Rav Oshaya,
but one minute, we have a ברייתא Baraita of רב אושעיא Rav
Oshaya that debates one of these points that says the following, and
this is broken up more into sections. קוצץ אדם על ידי עצמו
ועל ידי אשתו, Kotzetz Adam Al Yadei Atzmo Ve'Al Yadei Ishto, a
person can negotiate for himself and for his wife to give up
the right to eat, אבל לא על ידי בהמתו, Aval Lo Al
Yadei Behemto, but not for his בהמה. Behemah. So there you go,
Dov, it's sort of separated as you know it's like that's a
different category. Okay. ועל ידי בנו ובתו גדולים, Ve'Al Yadei Beno U'Vito
Gedolim, and he can negotiate for his adult children, אבל לא על
ידי בנו ובתו קטנים, Aval Lo Al Yadei Beno U'Vito Ketanim, not
his minor children. וקוצץ הוא על ידי עבדו ושפחתו הכנענים בין גדולים
בין קטנים. Vekotzetz Hu Al Yadei Avdo VeShifchato HaKena'anim Bein Gedolim Bein
Ketanim. But he can negotiate for his. for his slaves regardless of
if they're adults or minors. So the debate of these two ברייתות
Baraitas is the second one allows him to negotiate for his minor
children, for his minor slaves. Why is that? So מאי לאו, mai
lav, are we not talking, אידי ואידי במעלה להם מזונות, idei ve'idei
be-ma'aleh lahem mezonot, both cases is that he's feeding them and entitled
to their work. So therefore what's the issue then of whether he
can negotiate his slaves? ובהא קמיפלגי, u've-ha ka-miflagi, this is this is
what's between it. דמר סבר משלו הוא אוכל, de-mar savar mi-shelo hu
ochel, it's part of the salary and therefore he can negotiate since
he feeds them, he's entitled to their work, and therefore he can
negotiate the the slave's salary, even the minor slaves. ומר סבר משמיא
הוא אוכל, u-mar savar mi-shamaya hu ochel, no, it's from heaven and
it's not part of the salary and therefore he cannot negotiate the
minor slave's work because he's not entitled to it. No, says the
גמרא, Gemara, that's not the case. דכולי עלמא משלו הוא אוכל, de-kulei
alma mi-shelo hu ochel, it's part of the salary. ולא קשיא, ve-lo
kashya, what's the debate? כאן בשאין מעלה להם מזונות kan be-she-ein ma'aleh
lahem mezonot וברייתא במעלה להם מזונות. ve-Baraita be-ma'aleh lahem mezonot. The question
is is he feeding them or not? In the first case he's
not feeding them, so even though it is salary, he's not entitled
to their salary, so he can't negotiate it away, and in the
second case he is feeding them and he is entitled to their
salary and he can negotiate it. So now the גמרא Gemara says
okay, במאי אוקימתא, be-mai okimta, how did you say the second case
where he can negotiate the minor slave's salary? במעלה להם מזונות, be-ma'aleh
lahem mezonot,
that he's feeding them, he's entitled to their salary, it's part of
their salary, he can negotiate. אי הכי, ei hachi, if that's true,
קטנים נמי ניקוץ? ktanim nami nikoetz?
The same ברייתא Baraita that says he can negotiate for his minor
slaves says he can't negotiate for his minor children. Why not? If
it's salary and he's entitled to the salary of his minor slaves
and entitled to the salary of his minor children, if he can
negotiate his salary of a slave he should be able to negotiate
over his children. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שכרייה דבנו ובתו
קטנים לא זכי ליה רחמנא. schariah de-vno u-vito ktanim lo zachu lei
Rachmana. He does not have a right to negotiate away. He can
be entitled to the salary of his minor sons and daughters, but
not a type of a salary that is basically just giving them
food to eat. Okay, now actually תוספות Tosafot says the תורה Torah
didn't give him a right. Really the father's rights to his kid's
earnings is really rabbinic. Although for his son's earnings it's rabbinic, for
his daughter's it might be biblical. So the רחמנא Rachmana here might
be לאו דוקא, lav davka, but the point is that although we
give the father the right to the children's earnings, he does not
have a right to take it away if their earnings are basically
just giving them food to eat. Okay, so therefore that he cannot
negotiate away even though he's entitled to it, but he can negotiate
it away for his slaves.
Okay, why do we give him the right to benefit by causing
his קטנים ktanim to suffer? Right,
exactly.
Okay, so do you want to finish to the משנה? Mishnah? You
guys want to give me two more minutes? Okay, fine. So the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Now במאי אוקימתא למתניתין? be-mai okimta le-matnitin?
What did you say our משנה Mishnah because the first thing about
negotiating for your wife and kids is really the next משנה Mishnah
we're going to read on צ"ג ע"א. tzadik gimmel amud aleph. So
that משנה Mishnah said adults you can always do, minors you can
never do. Doesn't matter slaves, children, whatever. So במאי אוקימתא למתניתין, be-mai
okimta le-matnitin, what did you say our משנה Mishnah was talking about?
בשאין מעלה להם מזונות. be-she-ein ma'aleh lahem mezonot. He's not feeding them
and therefore he's not entitled to their salary. And therefore he can't
negotiate. Even if we look at this as salary, he can't negotiate
it if for minors because he's not feeding them and he's not
entitled to it. So the גמרא Gemara says הניחא למאן דאמר אין
הרב יכול לומר לעבד עשה עמי ואיני זנך. ha-nicha le-man de-amar ein
ha-rav yachol lomar le-eved asei imi ve-eini zanecha. That's good if a
master cannot say to the slave, I refuse to feed you and
you still have to work for me. So then you could say
because he's not feeding them, he's not entitled to their work. Okay,
even with a slave you're not entitled to their work if you're
not feeding them. שפיר, shapir, that makes sense. אלא למאן דאמר יכול
הרב לומר לעבד עשה עמי ואיני זנך, ela le-man de-amar yachol ha-rav
lomar le-eved asei imi ve-eini zanecha, but if a master can refuse
to feed a slave and nevertheless be entitled to his work, okay,
if that's true, then he should still be entitled to the work
of his minor slaves. I don't care if he's feeding them or
not feeding them, right? It's slaves, he's entitled to their work. Why
can't he negotiate? It would if you think that this eating is
a salary,
then according to this opinion even if he's not feeding them he
could negotiate. So מאי איכא למימר, mai ika le-meimar, what can you
say? אלא אידי ואידי בשאין מעלה להם מזונות, ela idei ve-idei be-she-ein
ma'aleh lahem mezonot, fine, both the משנה Mishnah and the ברייתא Baraita
he's not feeding them, ובהא פליגי, u've-ha pligi, this is the debate.
דמר סבר יכול, de-mar savar yachol, that a master is entitled to
his slave's work even if he doesn't feed them. And that's the
ברייתא Baraita that says that he can negotiate away his minor slave's
eating rights because he's entitled to that even without feeding them. But
he can't for his minors because he's not feeding. So if he's
not feeding his kids he's not entitled to their work, but he's
not feeding his slaves he still is entitled to the work. So
and therefore according to that he can negotiate away even his minor
slave's rights.
So he's making a lot of money, he's getting the
he's not feeding them, exactly, exactly, exactly, so finally
he's getting the salary and not allowing the kids to nibble.
Exactly. ומר סבר אין יכול, u-mar savar ein yachol, no, he's not
entitled to their work and he can't negotiate it away. Okay, now
ורבי יוחנן דאמר יכול, ve-Rabbi Yochanan de-amar yachol, now according to Rabbi
Yochanan is the one that says a
master is entitled to the work of the slave. even without feeding
them. So
according to
him, יכול רב, Yakhol Rav, שביק מתניתין ועבדי כברייתא, Shevik Matniten Ve-avdi
Ke-baraita,
would he abandon the משנה Mishna and go like the ברייתא? Baraita?
Because you just got through saying that the ברייתא Baraita that says
that he can negotiate his minor slave's work holds that you can
not feed a slave and be entitled to the work. And the
משנה Mishna disagrees. Well, why would רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, who we
know always loves the סתם משנה, Stam Mishna, why would he go
by the opinion of the ברייתא Baraita that says that you are
not, that because according to this only the ברייתא Baraita says you're
not, that you are entitled to the work?
So it's a general claim now?
Right. אלא דכולי עלמא משלו הוא אוכל. Ela De-kulei Alma Mi-shelo Hu
Okhel. Fine.
All this was playing it out assuming that it was משלו, Mi-shelo,
was part of the salary. And are you entitled to the salary
if you're feeding them, if you're not feeding them, if you're slaves,
if you're children, etc.? Let's go back to the other way. It's
all מן השמים. Min Ha-shamayim. Okay, if it's מן השמים, Min Ha-shamayim,
therefore you're not entitled, you as the master or or the father
are not entitled to it. The most you can do is represent
other people, implicitly represent them if they're בני דעת, Benei Daat, which
is the assumption of the משנה. Mishna. Okay, דכולי עלמא מן השמים
הוא אוכל, De-kulei Alma Min Ha-shamayim Hu Okhel, ולא מצי קציץ. Ve-lo
Matzi Katzitz.
You are not in a position to really negotiate, negotiate away because,
you know, it's a right the תורה Torah gives you, so it
can't even really be negotiated. So ומאי קציץ? U-mai Katzitz? דאמר רבי
אושעיא, De-amar Rabbi Oshaya, מזונות. Mezonot. So when we actually say a
קציץ, Katzitz, what we really mean is מזונות. Mezonot. One minute, let
me just check רש"י. Rashi.
Ah. So we really don't mean that you're going to give me
a higher salary and I won't have a right to eat, etc.,
because you can't compromise the right to eat. That's מן השמים. Min
Ha-shamayim. So what we really mean is we're agreeing that you feed
us a lot beforehand to stuff us up in order that we'll,
you know, we won't eat when we're actually working, okay, which is
not פשט Pshat at all and the גמרא Gemara anyway rejects it.
גמרא Gemara says no, you can't say that. דכוותה גבי בהמה תבן
וכרסנה, De-khavateh Gabi Behemah Teven Ve-kharsana, so then why can't you do
it for your animal? Remember one of the ones you couldn't do
it for was your animal. So if all you're talking about is
giving them food beforehand, you're allowed to give food to the animal
beforehand to prevent it from eating. Okay, fine. אלא בהא קמיפלגי. Ela
Be-ha Ka-miflagi. This is the debate. דמר סבר משלו הוא אוכל, De-mar
Savar Mi-shelo Hu Okhel, one says that it's yours, and if it's
yours and it's part of the salary, it's also the slave's, and
therefore you can negotiate it away, okay, because it's the your slave's
salary, you can negotiate it even minor slaves. ומר סבר מן השמים
הוא אוכל, U-mar Savar Min Ha-shamayim Hu Okhel, that it's from heaven,
so you can't negotiate it for your kids and for your minors
and slaves. But as adults, you can basically say we're not going
to use the right the תורה Torah has given us if you
promise to give us more salary. That you can do if you're
adults, even if it's מן השמים. Min Ha-shamayim. But as kids, you
know, you can't compromise the rights the תורה Torah has given them
and it's not salary for you to be able to negotiate it.
Okay, we will end with that with having not resolved our bigger
question.